

Varvara Lazarenko

Address Nijmegen, The Netherlands

Telephone +31 6 2662 9839

E-mail varlazoa@gmail.com

Date of birth 29.12.1998 (26 years)

LinkedIn www.linkedin.com/in/varvara-lazo

PERSONAL STATEMENT

I am a curious and dedicated MSc graduate in Medical Biology with strong experience in molecular and cellular biology, advanced imaging, and *in vivo* models. My research interests focus on molecular neurobiology and the cellular mechanisms underlying neurodegeneration. I am motivated to learn new research methods and to grow within the academic field.

EDUCATION

09/2022 - 08/2024 MSc in Medical Biology - Radboud University, Nijmegen, The Netherlands

- ✓ <u>Specialisation</u>: Science, Management and Innovation
- ✓ GPA result: 7.63/10.00
- ✓ <u>Principal subjects</u>: Future of health, How Health Systems Work, Sustainable Innovation Management, Molecular and Cellular Neurobiology, Molecular Therapy, Trends in Stem Cell Biology
- ✓ <u>Master thesis</u>: «Potential added value of home telemonitoring technology in elderly care», GPA result: 8.00/10.00

09/2016 - 06/2020 BSc in Biology - Lomonosov Moscow State University (MSU), Moscow, Russia

- ✓ <u>Specialisation</u>: Human and Animal Physiology
- √ GPA result: 4.83/5.00
- ✓ <u>Principal subjects</u>: Human and animal physiology, Electrophysiology of excited cells, Physiology of central nervous and visceral systems, Physiology of circulation, Biochemistry, Immunology, Genetics, Microbiology, Embryology
- ✓ <u>Skills</u>: qPCR, RT-PCR, gel electrophoresis, wire myography, western blotting, ELISA, HPLC, microscopy, cell culture, immunohistochemistry, intracellular recording (microelectrodes, patch clamp), behaviour tests (open field test, elevated plus maze, light-dark box test)
- ✓ <u>Bachelor thesis</u>: «Role of TASK-1 channels in arterial tone regulation in different organs in rats», GPA result: 5.00/5.00

WORK EXPERIENCE

10/2024 - current Part-time staff while searching for a life sciences position Renato's Pizzeria - Nijmegen, The Netherlands

- ✓ Providing customer service
- √ Selling the restaurant's menu

02/2024 - 08/2024 Intern at <u>Digital Transformation of Rehabilitation Care</u>

HAN University of Applied Sciences - Nijmegen, The Netherlands

- ✓ Added value research of home telemonitoring in elderly care based on the HTA framework presented onto the Quadruple aim
- ✓ Deployment of surveys (22) in Dutch and interviewing (7) medical professionals in English on their home telemonitoring experience/attitude
- ✓ Cost-effectiveness analysis (Markov model cohort simulation) on home telemonitoring in elderly peripheral arterial disease (PAD) patients in the Netherlands

02/2023 - 08/2023 Intern at Neuronal Networks of Memory

Donders Institute - Nijmegen, The Netherlands

- ✓ Applied two-photon Ca²⁺ imaging and fluorescence microscopy to study neuronal activity of the retrosplenial cortex during social fear learning in vivo in mice
- ✓ Management of laboratory animals (GCaMP6 transgenic mice, handling & feeding, craniotomy)
- ✓ Computational analysis of the neuronal activity patterns (Python, DeepLabCut)

LABMGMU, LLC - Moscow, Russia

- ✓ Developing designs, synopses, protocols, investigator's brochures for more than 35 phase I, II, III clinical trials and bioequivalence trials
- ✓ More than 30 user interviews (testing the readability of pharmaceuticals' package leaflets)
- ✓ Advising on the number & design of (pre-)clinical studies for pharma clients
- ✓ Project management (control of the deadlines; compliance with the sponsor's requirements)
- ✓ Computational analysis of the obtained data (STATISTICA, GraphPad Prism)

10/2020 - 10/2021 Junior Research Assistant at Faculty of Biology

Lomonosov Moscow State University - Moscow, Russia

- ✓ Research on TASK-1 channels in rat arteries under varying pH conditions
- ✓ Physiological experiments (wire myography technique, rat coronary and renal arteries)
- ✓ Molecular experiments (RNA extraction, reverse transcription, qPCR, western blotting)
- ✓ Cell and tissue culture experiments (cultivation of arteries in the presence of methoxamine, isoproterenol, and H2O)
- ✓ Management of laboratory animals (Wistar rats: housing, care, breeding)
- ✓ Statistical analysis of the obtained data (STATISTICA, GraphPad Prism)
- ✓ Project management (experiment and research strategy planning)
- ✓ Presentation of the results at the <u>virtual conference ARTERY20</u>, 23-24 October 2020, and at the <u>Conference "Lomonosov-2021"</u>, 12-23 April 2021

SKILLS

Molecular and cellular biology: qPCR, RNA/DNA isolation, cloning, western blotting, ELISA, HPLC, cell/tissue culture

Microscopy and imaging: light microscopy, fluorescence microscopy, two-photon calcium imaging, immunohistochemistry

Neurobiology techniques: *in vivo* rodent models (ischaemia, preeclampsia, voluntary running), electrophysiology techniques (microelectrodes, patch clamp)

Digital: Python (beginner), DeepLabCut, STATISTICA, GraphPad Prism, Rotor-Gene Q Series, MS Office software

SCIENTIFIC JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- 1. Shvetsova Anastasia A., **Lazarenko Varvara S.**, Gaynullina Dina K., Tarasova Olga S., Schubert Rudolf (2022). TWIK-Related Acid-Sensitive Potassium Channels (TASK-1) Emerge as Contributors to Tone Regulation in Renal Arteries at Alkaline pH. *Frontiers in physiology*, *13*: 895863. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2022.895863
- 2. **Lazarenko Varvara**, Shvetsova Anastasia, Gaynullina Dina, Schubert Rudolph (2020). TASK-1 Channels Play an Anticontractile Role in Rat Septal Coronary Artery Under Pharmacological Blockade of Endothelium. *Artery Research*, 26(S1): S58. https://doi.org/10.2991/artres.k.201209.048
- 3. Borzykh A.A., Kuzmin I.V., Kiryukhina O.O., Selivanova E.K., Shvetsova A.A., **Lazarenko V.S.**, Los-Arkos Uvarova S., Nesterenko A.M., Tarasova O.S. (2020). Voluntary running training of female rats during gestation: characteristics of an experimental model [in Russian]. *Aviakosmicheskaya i Ekologicheskaya Meditsina*, *54*(2): 89–95. https://www.elibrary.ru/item.asp?id=42721639

CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

1. **Lazarenko V. S.**, Shvetsova A. A. (2021). Removal of the endothelium leads to augmented contractile responses in rat renal interlobar arteries under alkaline conditions [Abstract in Russian]. In I.A. Aleshkovsky, A.V. Andriyanov, E.A. Antipov & E.I. Zimakova (Eds.), *Materials of the International Youth Scientific Forum "LOMONOSOV-2021"*. MAKS Press, Moscow. https://lomonosov-msu.ru/archive/Lomonosov_2021/data/section_2_21890.htm

- 2. Tarasova O.S., Selivanova E.K., Borzykh A.A., Kiryukhina O.O., Shvetsova A.A., **Lazarenko V.S.**, Makukha Yu.A., Bogotskoy K.A., Ivanova A.D., Voronina Ya.A., Kuzmin V.S. (2021). Nitric oxide deficiency during prenatal development is accompanied by a change in the nervous regulation of the heart in postnatal ontogenesis [Abstract in Russian]. In R.I. Sepiashvili & M.A. Ostrovsky (Eds.), *VII Russian Congress on Physiology, Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, X Russian Symposium "Proteins and Peptides", VII Russian Biochemical Congress, VII CIS Congress on Physiology (Proceedings. Sochi–Dagomys, October 3-8, 2021), 1: 90-91. Pero Publishing House, Moscow.*
- 3. Shvetsova A.A., Selivanova E.K., Gaynullina D.K., Kiryukhina O.O., Borzykh A.A., **Lazarenko V.S.**, Los Arcos Uvarova S., Schubert R., Tarasova O.S. (2020). An increase in the anticontractile effect of potassium channels in the arteries of 2-week-old offspring of female rats with experimental preeclampsia [Abstract in Russian]. Proceedings of *VII All-Russian School-Conference with International Participation on Physiology and Pathology of Blood Circulation*, pp. 154-155. RA ILF, Moscow.
- 4. **Lazarenko V.S.**, Sebentsova E. A. (2019). Influence of DMSO on the physical and motor development in C57BL/6 mice [Abstract in Russian]. In I.A. Aleshkovsky, A.V. Andriyanov & E.A. Antipov (Eds.), *Materials of the International Youth Scientific Forum "LOMONOSOV-2019"*. MAKS Press, Moscow. https://lomonosov-msu.ru/archive/Lomonosov_2019/data/section_2_16089.htm

CERTIFICATES

2023	A FELASA accredited course on Laboratory Animal Science (EU function B) at Radboudumc
2021	An upgrade training on ICH guidelines on Good Clinical Practice (GCP) at LABMGMU

ACADEMIC HONORS AND AWARDS

2022-2024	Awarded Orange Tulip Scholarship for the studies at Radboud University
2020-2021	Awarded MSU Increased State Academic Scholarship for scientific and academic achievements
2021	Second prize-winner in the Lomonosov Universiade on modern problems of biology

LANGUAGES

Russian (native), English (fluent – C_2), German (intermediate – B_1 - B_2), Dutch (low intermediate – A_2 - B_1), French (beginner - A_1)

VOLUNTEERING ACTIVITY

2024	Mentorship of the international exchange and Master's students at the Radboud Intro
2023	Organization of the BBB Career Event 2023, Nijmegen
2022-2023	Organization of volleyball tournaments in the international volleyball group at Radboud
2018-2021	Mentorship of the first-year students at Faculty of Biology, MSU, Moscow

HOBBIES

Animals (horses & dogs), volleyball, reading, drawing, guitar playing, traveling

REFERENCES

- 1. Arie Kim, PhD, Assistant Research Scientist at Columbia University Irving Medical Center a supervisor of the first master's internship at Donders Institute, arie.kim@nyspi.columbia.edu
- 2. Anastasia Shvetsova, PhD, Leading Research Scientist at the Department of Human and Animal Physiology at Lomonosov Moscow State University, a supervisor of the bachelor's internship and the bachelor's thesis, anastasiashvetsova92@gmail.com
- **Extra**: 3. Geert Frederix, PhD, Associate professor Health Technology Assessment at UMC Utrecht and Applied Professor Digital Transformation in healthcare at HAN University of Applied Sciences a supervisor of the master's thesis, geert.frederix@han.nl